We introduce Proxy Policy Steering,
an inference-time adaptation method for robotics foundation models.
Generalist policies carry broad manipulation priors from large-scale data.
However, they still struggle in downstream tasks that
are underrepresented in the training distribution.
Direct fine-tuning methods tackle this by modifying the base policy
weights, reshaping the base policy’s action distribution.
While this effectively adapts the policy behavior,
it can overfit to the limited demonstrations and lose the general priors.
Existing steering methods, like DSRL, change the initial noise or
flow-matching process to select actions suitable for the task.
However, the actions are still sampled from the base
distribution and do not deliver novel behaviors.
How could generalist policies learn new skills without losing the base prior?
We propose Proxy Policy Steering.
Instead of reshaping the base action distribution,
we estimate how task supervision would change it.
Specifically, we distill the base policy into a lightweight
reference proxy under task observations.
We then fine-tune this proxy under task supervision to obtain a task proxy.
At inference, we take the velocity predictions of all three models,
subtract the reference velocity and add the task velocity.
This residual captures the task-induced shift,
steering the policy to approximate the fine-tuned action distribution.
Facing a state where the base policy needs guidance to locate the correct
grasping position, the residual steers the base toward the task proxy,
which guides the robot to show novel task behavior for correct grasping.
In a state that is not covered in the task demonstrations due to
a failed grasp, the base policy shows generic recovery behavior.
Here, our proxy policies share the same overfitting errors, making the residual near zero.
Therefore, the base retains control and recovers from the grasping failure.
When the proxy policies agree with the base policy. The robot follows the shared behavior.
By combining proxy residual with the base prior, PPS injects task guidance while retaining
the general priors of the base model, achieving robust manipulation in downstream tasks.
We evaluate PPS on 12 tasks, spanning long-horizon goals,
deformable and articulated objects, and diverse skills.
PPS outperforms LoRA fine-tuning, previous steering methods, and trained-from-scratch policies.
Since PPS keeps the base model intact, it preserves the general priors from the base model.
This helps the policy recover under human interventions even though
no recovery behavior is collected in the demonstrations.
Whereas LoRA fine-tuning can overfit to the small-scale task-specific
demonstrations and overwrite parts of the manipulation priors learned
during pre-training, causing it to fail under perturbations.
PPS also enables injecting information from additional modalities into the base model,
such as using point cloud to locate textureless objects and
leveraging audio inputs to find the sound source.
Thanks for watching!